<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Rishav Dahal</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Rishav Dahal</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.140.2</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 11:32:00 +0545</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Improving OCR Accuracy on Document Images</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/blogs/improving-ocr-accuracy-on-document-images/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 11:32:00 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/blogs/improving-ocr-accuracy-on-document-images/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;improving-ocr-accuracy-on-document-images-a-step-by-step-approach&#34;&gt;Improving OCR Accuracy on Document Images: A Step-by-Step Approach&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Optical Character Recognition (OCR) is revolutionizing the way we digitize and process documents. Whether it’s converting a scanned document into editable text or extracting data from receipts, OCR technology is increasingly relied upon across industries. However, one of the main challenges faced by OCR systems is their accuracy, especially when dealing with noisy or poorly scanned images. In this blog, I’ll walk you through the techniques I used to improve OCR accuracy on document images by leveraging pre-processing methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OCR Code Compiler</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/projects/ocr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 11:32:00 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/projects/ocr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;unveiling-ocrcompiler-20---bridging-ocr-and-code-compilation&#34;&gt;Unveiling OCRcompiler 2.0 - Bridging OCR and Code Compilation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the world of software development, innovation often lies at the intersection of disparate technologies. &lt;strong&gt;OCRcompiler 2.0&lt;/strong&gt;, hosted on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rishav-dahal/OCRcompiler2.0&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, is a prime example of this. Combining Optical Character Recognition (OCR) with multi-language code compilation, this project takes document digitization and code execution to a whole new level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;overview-of-ocrcompiler-20&#34;&gt;Overview of OCRcompiler 2.0&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OCRcompiler 2.0 is designed to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extract text from scanned or image-based documents using OCR.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parse and compile code written in multiple programming languages such as Python, C, C++, Java, and JavaScript.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide a seamless interface for users to upload images, process code, and view execution results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project not only automates tedious tasks like manual text extraction but also allows developers to execute and validate code directly from scanned documents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;hello-im-rishav-dahal-&#34;&gt;Hello, I&amp;rsquo;m Rishav Dahal! 👋&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a passionate &lt;strong&gt;Software Engineering student&lt;/strong&gt; at Nepal College of Information Technology (NCIT) with a strong interest in &lt;strong&gt;web development, AI, and creative problem-solving&lt;/strong&gt;. Currently based in Bhaktapur, Nepal, I thrive on building innovative projects that bridge technology and real-world needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;-what-i-do&#34;&gt;🔧 What I Do&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Full-Stack Development&lt;/strong&gt;: Crafting interactive websites and software applications using Python, Django, and modern frameworks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AI &amp;amp; Machine Learning&lt;/strong&gt;: Developing solutions like medical chatbots, attendance systems, and OCR tools with NLP and computer vision.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creative Design&lt;/strong&gt;: Designing graphics (Figma) and editing videos to bring ideas to life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;-projects--achievements&#34;&gt;🚀 Projects &amp;amp; Achievements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Built &lt;strong&gt;Shiskhya&lt;/strong&gt; (lecture summarization software) and &lt;strong&gt;Swashya&lt;/strong&gt; (centralized medical records app) during hackathons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Created a &lt;strong&gt;BERT-based medical chatbot&lt;/strong&gt; and an &lt;strong&gt;AI attendance system&lt;/strong&gt; using OpenCV and deep learning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Volunteered as an IT Cordinator and Graphic Designer for &lt;strong&gt;HULT Prize at NCIT 2022&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;-technical-skills&#34;&gt;🛠️ Technical Skills&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Programming Languages:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;code&gt;Python&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;Java&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;C&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;C++&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
